Wolcott, John; Papers apap294
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
John Wolcott Papers
1954-1992
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Wolcott, John R.
apap294
0.7 cubic ft. processed to date
The John Wolcott Papers document the revival of the historic Pinxter Festival in Albany, New York between 1972-1992.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
John Wolcott donated his materials in 2007 to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives. In 2013 Wolcott donated an additional 26 cubic feet of materials which will be processed at a later date.
Biographical Sketch
John Wolcott was chairman of the Pinxter Committee of Albany, also called the People’s Pinxter Festival Committee, which coordinated the annual Pinxter Festival. The festival is known as Pinxter, Pinxter Sunday or Pinkster, Dutch for Pentecost, and as Whitsuntide, the English term for Pentecost.
During the colonial period, Pinxter celebrations were held throughout eastern New York in communities of Dutch origins. Africans played a major role in organizing Pinxter, adding African music and dance to the festivities. In 1811 the Common Council of the City of Albany passed a Whitsuntide Holiday law which banned the essential elements of the festival and, as a result, the festival died out.
In 1971, Pinxter was revived in Albany and celebrated on Sundays during Tulip Fest in Washington Park with craft vendors and musicians. It was often advertised as an illegal festival. Wolcott wrote several letters asking the 1811 law be repealed. The Whitsuntide Holiday Law was repealed in 2011, two hundred years after it was enacted.
Scope and Contents
The John Wolcott Papers contain materials related to the planning and advertising of Pinxter Festivals in Albany, New York. The collection includes festival posters, fliers, photographs, news clippings, hand written notes, correspondence and programs of similar festivals, including a early souvenir Tulip Fest envelope. Craft vendors were a major part of the festivities and the contact information for many of them is included. Information about historic Pinxter festivals, Albany’s relevant laws and policies, and a small collection of colonial Dutch recipes were used in the planning process.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized chronologically. There are no series.
Neighborhood and Community Associations; Albany, New York; Folk festivals New York (State); Pentecost Festival; Albany (N.Y.); Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence; Fliers (printed matter); Posters; Black-and-white photographs; Programs (documents); Newspapers; Wolcott, John R.
- Tulip Fest, 1954 (Box 1 (John Wolcott Papers ), Folder 1)
- Pinxter Fest, 1972 (Box 1 (John Wolcott Papers ), Folder 2)
- KITE News Clippings, 1972-1980 (Oversized 1, Folder 1)
- Pinxter Fest, 1973 (Box 1 (John Wolcott Papers ), Folder 3)
- Pinxter Fest, 1976 (Box 1 (John Wolcott Papers ), Folder 4)
- Pinxter Fest Posters, 1976-1982; Undated (Oversized 1, Folder 2)
- Niskayuna Folk Festival, 1977 (Box 1 (John Wolcott Papers ), Folder 5)
- Northeast Craft Fair, 1977 (Box 1 (John Wolcott Papers ), Folder 6)
- Pinxter Fest, 1977 (Box 1 (John Wolcott Papers ), Folder 7)
- Pinxter Fest, 1978 (Box 1 (John Wolcott Papers ), Folder 8)
- Pinxter Fest, 1979 (Box 1 (John Wolcott Papers ), Folder 9)
- The Entertainer News Clippings, 1979-1980 (Oversized 1, Folder 3)
- Pinxter Fest, 1980 (Box 1 (John Wolcott Papers ), Folder 10)
- Pinxter Fest, 1981 (Box 1 (John Wolcott Papers ), Folder 11)
- Pinxter Fest, 1982 (Box 1 (John Wolcott Papers ), Folder 12)
- Pinxter Fest, 1983 (Box 1 (John Wolcott Papers ), Folder 13)
- Pinxter Fest, 1984 (Box 1 (John Wolcott Papers ), Folder 14)
- Pinxter Fest, 1985 (Box 1 (John Wolcott Papers ), Folder 15)
- Pinxter Fest, 1992 (Box 1 (John Wolcott Papers ), Folder 16)
- Albany City Special Event Policy Statement, Undated (Box 1 (John Wolcott Papers ), Folder 17)
- Craft Vendor Business Cards and Flyers, Undated (Box 1 (John Wolcott Papers ), Folder 18)
- Craft Vendor Notebook, Undated (Box 1 (John Wolcott Papers ), Folder 19)
- Loose Leaf Notes, Undated (Box 1 (John Wolcott Papers ), Folder 20)
- Pintxer Fest, Undated (Box 1 (John Wolcott Papers ), Folder 21)
- Pinxter Fest Photographs, Undated (Box 2 (John Wolcott Papers ), Folder 1)
- Planning Notebook, Undated (Box 2 (John Wolcott Papers ), Folder 2-3)
- Recipes, Undated (Box 2 (John Wolcott Papers ), Folder 4)
- Research Materials, Undated (Box 2 (John Wolcott Papers ), Folder 5)
- Treasures from Eleanor Skelton Cash, Poetry, Undated (Box 2 (John Wolcott Papers ), Folder 6)